Guide to the Luis Alberto Guajardo Papers on the History of Coahuila
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Luis Alberto Guajardo Papers on the History of Coahuila
1845-1936
1936-1936
WA MSS S-668
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.92
(7 boxes)
Typescripts, notes, and typewritten transcriptions of original source material concerning the development of Luis Alberto Guajardo's Apuntes, Datos, y Noticias Para la Historia de Coahuila. Topics documented include the history of Coahuila and Mexico, particularly Monclova; the history of the presidio of Santa Rosa, including its mines; the history of indigenous people in the region; the military feats of Juan de Ugalde; the wars of independence of 1810 and 1821; the cholera epidemics of 1833 and 1849; the campaign into Texas in 1836; and the Mexican Revolution of 1910 and 1911.
Guajardo, Luis Alberto
Arrangement
The original order in which this collection was arranged has been maintained.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Luis Alberto Guajardo (1872-1925) was a general in the Mexican Army. He was born in Músquiz, Coahuila and participated in the Mexican Revolution. His military travels allowed him to visit local record offices in Coahuila and research the history of the region, as well as make copies of original documents. This research led to the formulation of Apuntes Datos y Noticias Para la Historia de Coahuila, a history of the Coahuila region.
Scope and Contents
Typescripts, notes, and typewritten transcriptions of original source material concerning the development of Luis Alberto Guajardo's Apuntes, Datos, y Noticias Para la Historia de Coahuila. Topics documented include the history of Coahuila and Mexico, particularly Monclova; the history of the presidio of Santa Rosa, including its mines; the history of indigenous people in the region; the military feats of Juan de Ugalde; the wars of independence of 1810 and 1821; the cholera epidemics of 1833 and 1849; the campaign into Texas in 1836; and the Mexican Revolution of 1910 and 1911.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Frederick W. Beinecke, 1959.
Related Materials
Associated material: Luis Alberto Guajardo Collection of Músquiz, Mexico Records (WA MSS S-1482). Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Yale University.
Cholera -- Mexico; Indians of Mexico -- Mexico -- Coahuila and Texas; Mines and mineral resources -- Mexico; Mineral industries -- Mexico; Coahuila and Texas (Mexico) -- History; Mexico -- History -- 1821-1861; Mexico -- History -- To 1810; Mexico -- History -- Revolution, 1910-1920; Mexico -- Politics and government -- 1821-1861; Monclova (Mexico); Texas -- History -- Revolution, 1835-1836; Mexican-American Border Region; Guajardo, Luis Alberto; Iturbide, Agustín de, 1783-1824; Ugalde, Juan de, 1729-1816
- Tables of content and duplicate notes, undated (Box 1)
- Actuaciones de la Epoca de la Conquista, 1695, undated
- Denuncios de Minas en el Cerro del Mercado, 1690, undated
- Varios Documentos Antiguos, 1763-1785, undated
- Creacion del Presidio de Santa Rosa y Documentacion Comprobativa, 1779, undated
- Real Presidio de Rio Grande, 1782-1787, undated
- Real Presidio de Rio Grande y El Capitan Don Juan de Ugalde, 1778-1788, undated
- Juicio de Residencia de Nicolás Guaxardo, 1700 (copy 1 of 3), undated
- Juicio de Residencia de Nicolás Guaxardo, 1700 (copy 2 of 3), undated
- Juicio de Residencia de Nicolás Guaxardo, 1700 (copy 3 of 3), undated
- Transcriptions related to Nicolás Guaxardo, undated
- Assorted drafts from the Apuntes, undated
- Mandamiento de Duque de Albuquerque, 1658, undated
- Visita Oficial de Governador Tueros, 1785, undated
- Disputa entre el Virrey Don Manuel Flores y El Cabaliero de Castro, 1791, undated
- Unedited notes on 1800-1810, undated
- Estado de la España Hasta Fines de 1809 y Varios Oficios Superiores: Génesis de la Insurrección, 1801-1811, undated (Box 2)
- Comunicaciones y Decretos de los años de 1812-1821, undated
- Prision de los Primeros Heroes Insurgentes de 1810 y Su Caida en Bajan, Coahuila: Apuntes de Fray Gregorio de la Concepcion, 1810-1811, undated
- Apuntes para la Historia de la Revolucion del Año de 1810: Escrito por un Compañero del Señor Hidalgo, undated; 2
- Génesis de la Insurrección, 1810-1811, undated
- Estado de España en 1810 y Génesis de la Insurrección, 1810, undated
- Assorted notes on the insurrection, 1810-1811, undated
- Typed transcripts of decrees of 1812-1818, undated
- Manuscript copies of correspondence from local offices, 1804-1835, undated
- Data and decrees on regions in Coahuila, 1819-1836, undated
- Notes on the years 1821-1822, undated (Box 3)
- Iturbide, 1822-1823, undated
- Chronology for 1821-1832, undated
- Actos de Ayuntamiento del Presidio de Santa Rosa, 1821-1836, undated
- Datos históricos, tomados directamente de sus originales, 1821-1835, undated
- Proyecto Canal Tehuantepec, 1824-1826, undated
- Notes on Coahuila y Texas, 1823-1825, undated
- Datos históricos, tomados directamente de sus originales, 1824-1826, undated
- Notes on 1827-1829, undated
- Notes on 1828-1829, undated
- Notes on 1829-1830, undated
- Copies of notes for the Apuntes, 1831-1839, undated
- Copies of notes for the Apuntes, 1832-1833, undated
- Notes for the Apuntes, 1833-1849, undated
- Invasión del Cólera Chico en la República, 1833 y la Campaña de Texas, undated
- De Mineria - Coahuila, undated
- Comunicaciones y Decretos, 1831-1832, undated
- Bocetos del Desierto: Novela Histórica por L. Alberto Guajardo, undated
- Comunicaciones y Decretos de Santa Rosa, 1833-1835, undated
- Notes and statistical information for Coahuila, including Seminoles, Organización de Texas, Monclova, undated
- Copies of notes on the Campaña de Texas, 1836, undated
- Notes on campaigns in Texas and against the Indians, including the Comanches, Lipanes, and Mezcaleros, 1837-1845, undated
- La Indiada Grande, 1839, undated
- Statistical information for Monclova and other parts of the Rio Grande, 1841-1842, undated
- Cuarta Epoca de Apuntes y Noticias Para la Historia de Coahuila, 1850-1873, undated; 2 (Box 4)
- Acusación politica, firmada por sus autores y presentada ante D. Ramón Corral, Vice-Presidente de la República, 1904, undated
- Revolucion de 1910, Apuntes de L. Alberto Guajardo, undated
- Notes on 1842-1847, undated
- El Asalto a la Indiada Grande en el Pozo y El Ataque a la Hacienda de la Mota en 1848, undated
- Cholera in Santa Rosa Maria del Sacramento, 1849, undated
- Una Campaña al Norte de Coahuila: La Batalla de la Rosita, undated
- Informe de la Comision Pesquisidora de la Frontera del Norte al Ejecutivo de la Union, 1873 (2 copies), undated
- Costumbres Indios para la Historia de Coahuila, undated; 3 (Box 6)
- Visita a las Minas de Santa Rosa, 1785, undated
- Miscelánea Histórica, undated; 2
- La Tribu Quickapoó: Antecedentes y Vocabulario del Idioma Quickapoó y Su Equivalencia en Español, 1936, undated; 2
- Noticia sobre el Padre Vetancurt, undated
- Miscelánea Histórica, undated
- Correspondencia con el Dr. Francisco Vásquez Gomez, 1926-1936
  Scope and Contents
  Includes two letters to J. Frank Dobie at University of Texas
- Presidio de la Babia y Otros Fuertes, 1774 drafts and duplicates, undated; 2 (Box 7)
- Creacion del Presidio de Santa Rosa, 1736, undated
- Actas del Ayuntamiento de Santa Rosa de 1821 hasta 1834, undated
- Notes on the history of Santa Rosa, undated
- De Mineria en el Presidio de Santa Rosa, 1845, 1896, undated
  Includes two manuscript petitions to the Diputacion de Mineria de Santa Rosa from the towns of Monclova and Cienega, 1845, 1896
- Al Derredor de la Lumbre: Las Casas Consistoriales de Santa Rosa, undated
- Notes on the history Monclova, undated
- Noticias sobre el Agua del Rio de Monclova, undated
- Notes on Monclova: Cuarto Cuaderno, undated
- Copias de Algunos Documentos Pertenecientes a los Pueblos de San Francisco y San Miguel, Anexos a la Ciudad de Monclova, 1907, undated
- Historia de Monclova, 1810-1811: Los Insurgentes de la Primera Epoca de la Independencia Mexicana, undated
- Historia de Monclova: Real Provision de Don Pedro Sebreán, 1744, undated